the goal that he suggested in this post
of him doing this insanely heavy double
is that he wants to lock out 500 kg he
would be the only athlete ever to do
that outside of the super heavyweight
class Christy oconnell is kind of like
built in a lab for high rocks right high
level CrossFit Games athlete five top 10
finishes clearly Has the strength but a
background in endurance sport she was a
Collegiate swimmer she was also
competitive triathlete this was probably
one of my worst meets I felt
uncomfortable Rusty my technique was all
over over the place that's the quote so
like okay two unofficial World Records
your sixth national title and you're
still
like
medium hello folks and welcome back to
strength weekly the weekly YouTube show
that keeps you up to date from every
corner of the barbell game we have a big
episode we have a
1,47 lb squat for a double Nick Walker
returns to training to try and qualify
for the 2024 Mr Olympia spoiler alert
he's not already qualified a former top
level CrossFit Games athlete looks to be
a problem for other competitors in high
level high rocks and Russell orhei well
he's back to the platform he's doing big
things he's breaking records
unofficially but he's still unhappy we
get into that and more I'm David Thomas
to from barb. comom joined by the
incomparable Phil lechman Phil of these
four
stories which would you enter a cage
match against you know I think if I was
going to get destroyed by any of these
stories it would have to be Nick Walker
because he just got over an injury and
if I'm gonna get injured in the cage
match it feels only balanced fair and
balanced well Phil if you wouldn't mind
me doing a favor I'm always the one to
intro things but you know what you're
writing a lot of the news on barbend
you're editing more of the news on Barb
Ben would you
mind introducing their first story of
the day which is a
1,47 PB squat for a double in training
if he'll take us in we're going to mix
it up a little bit so the story is about
Zahir Cuda yarov squatting 475 kgrs for
a double in wraps raw raw in wraps
there's raw without wraps which is a KNE
sleeves and then there's raw in wraps
okay great now that that's out of the
way so on March 17th he shared a video
of him doing this double and what's a
why this is a big deal is that he has
bounced back and forth between 125 kgs
and 140 kgs in competitive powerlifting
the goal that he suggested in this post
of him doing this insanely heavy double
is that he wants to lock out 500 kgs now
the big deal about that is if he were to
successfully lock out 500 Kilograms raw
and wraps in competition he would be the
only athlete ever to do that outside of
the super heavyweight class now that's a
big deal because that's like okay when
once you're super heavyweight you can be
as you can be as heavy and big as you
want and mass moves mass and then you
know like the top guys I have here Dan
Bell obviously he's got the 505 Kil
squat which is the heaviest of all time
and then you have uh two other athletes
that have both scored 500 Kilograms but
nobody outside of super heavyweight has
done it before so if karov can do it now
that that's that's a headline for a
future strength weekly that that's
that's a headline for a future strength
weekly and I think the context is
important here because we do see
athletes under the super heavyweight
category so in the not heaviest
powerlifting categories doing pretty
ridiculous things on the deadlift uh and
there's actually some interesting
physics physical elements there for
example athletes are a little bit might
actually be able to deadlift more
sometimes because they're able to get a
better grip on the barbell and also just
some of the proportions they're able to
get in better positions more conducive
to world record deadlifts so sometimes
actually we will see even at World
Championship level events the heaviest
deadlifts coming from non super
heavyweight athletes bench press yeah
super heavyweights have a have a a big
Advantage there on the bench press we
generally see them lift the most but for
squats it's very rare that you see
someone not in the super heavyweight
category inching up close to what the
super Heavies are doing in the squad
right having more mass is simply a
benefit in the squad so what Zahir is
potentially doing is throwing his hat in
the ring for one of the heaviest raw
with WRA squats of all time and this 475
kilo double AKA around 1047 pound double
is a good indication I think of what he
could do now Zahir has been at the top
rungs of the power ofing game for about
11 years I mean he really kind of burst
onto the scene in like 2013 is and
you're right he's bounced around between
some different weight categories dude is
energetic on the platform I'm going to
be honest he looks like he could scare a
barbell right out of the rack right with
the way he like just approaches these
weights and tears through them Zahir
squatting in competition 500 kilos as a
nons superheavy in in the not in not the
heaviest bodyweight category for me is
as impactful as Dan Bell squatting 505
as a super heavy now the current world
record in the in the squat for raw with
WPS is 480 kg that's by James Cersei
which is the same weight as karov has
hit at 125 so he has matched the world
world record in a weight class above him
so it's not unusual if he were to score
at 140 the world record or Tyler world
record in the super Heavies what if he
squats 508 as 140 kilo athlete like what
like what if let's just have some fun
with this for a double he's 30 kilograms
away from the all-time world record ever
that Dan Bell has right so if if he were
to chip just chip if he would have just
chip to 505 right yeah just chip to 505
if he would to hit if he were to hit
505 uh and a half that's the entire
episode of strength weekly next time
that's the entire we we're not talking
about anything else because the the the
the strength of world breaks at that
point what do weight classes even mean
anymore Up Is Down left is right yeah I
I I'm absolutely thrilled for that I'm
not going to call it an inevitability
but if it happens we're going to be
reporting to you now let's move over to
someone who is not squatting 475 kilos
but maybe looks like he potentially
could bodybuilding different it's about
what you look like not how much weight
you move anyway Nick Walker one of the
top men's open bodybuilders in the world
former Arnold Classic men's bodybuilding
Champion let's just put it this way Nick
Walker a contender eyes were on him for
a Podium finisher potentially the title
withdrew just weeks before the 2023
Olympia with a nasty hamstring tear and
it really changed the landscape of what
happened at the 2023 Olympia right with
Nick Walker out like we were
recalibrating and repr predicting what
our podiums looked like what our
predicted podiums looked like right
because I think a lot of us at barbin
had Nick Walker maybe not winning the
Olympia last year but but finishing on
the podium Nick Walker is back to
training back to training legs after
that hamstring tear and the interesting
thing is he actually has a bit of an
uphill battle in front of him because
this is kind of crazy to believe because
Walker's been one of the top men's open
bodybuilders in the world for a while
now he is not qualified for this year's
Mr
Olympia he has to win a pro show to
qualify for this year's Mr Olympia Phil
what does the competition calendar look
like for Nick and how is he planning to
get back to the Olympia stage yeah so
Nick's Next competition on the schedule
is on May 18th at the New York Pro so
the 2024 New York Pro which is a contest
he has won before he's not unfamiliar to
the stage he's been the champion of it
before but this is going to be his first
pro show after recovering from this
hamstring tear and if he can win he goes
to the Olympia now the reason that he's
not qualified is because he withdrew
from last year so he was qualified last
year because he had a Podium spot two
years ago so he finished in third place
behind hotti shupin and Derrick Lunsford
that was lunsford's first appearance
that you know put him on the map in the
men's open and now of course he's the
reigning Mr Olympia so top guys clearly
in the sport right now are shupin
Lunsford and uh Samson Duda but Nick
Walker has been this anomaly that's been
on the outside for a little bit because
of this injury and before he got injured
he had this trajectory where it seemed
like it was almost inevitable that he
was going to be the Mr Olympia at one
point you know he comes in his rookie
year on the Olympia stage he gets fifth
he comes back in he only ranks up he's
on the podium then he gets injured and
now he's coming back so it's like can he
have this sort of you know Rise From the
Ashes story and claim the title like
that's he's got really one of the most
interesting narratives going in if he
can win this New York Pro and just get
there now granted if he doesn't win the
New York Pro if he gets silver or if he
just misses or whatever he comes off the
mark he gets some feedback he still has
time he can compete in any other Pro
show as long as he gets a pro show win
before the cutoff date in September he
can compete at the Olympia in 2024 and
just just for reference the Olympia is
back to October we saw especially around
the pandemic the dates bounced around it
was in December November Olympia's back
to October my prediction is it stays
there that's kind of I think when we're
going to see the Olympia for a while we
had some short turnaround uh
competitions especially when things got
postponed during the pandemic Etc glad
to see Nick Walker help healthy glad to
see him training again interestingly he
started off this leg day you know when I
say I joked I inted someone who's not
squatting 475 kilos Nick Walker in what
he's posting on YouTube after training
is not going like he's going heavy but
not heavy for Nick Walker let's put
let's put this way he's really focusing
on pre fatiguing and pre fatiguing
isolation movements before he moves to
his compound movements so doing like leg
like leg extensions before he's moving
to you know hack squats leg presses
things like that Phil talk us through a
little bit about the methodology why a
top level bodybuilder might use you know
isolation single joint prefatigue
movements before they go onto their
compound movements you know that's
actually something that he has adjusted
over time you know he used to lift
extremely heavy like heavy was his forte
in the gym and he has since switched to
that because a lifting not as heavy even
though it's still heavy but not lifting
like max out heavy all the time is a lot
easier on the joints and being able to
do the prefatigue work before doing the
heavy compound movements look the goal
of bodybuilders and bodybuilding in
particular is Aesthetics you just want
the Aesthetics you want to look good on
stage and that means that you're looking
to Target the stimulus stimulus over
weight is what is valuable to these
bodybuilders so lifting super super
heavy this isn't powerlifting where like
your one rep max on the platform is what
matters it's only about how you look on
stage and the way to do that is muscle
stimulus and the way to achieve better
muscle stimulus is doing this sort of
prefatigue workout before your compound
movements because you're looking to
Target the muscles that you want to
highlight I don't know if you all
noticed but uh while Phil was actually
going into that very clear explanation
uh I was practicing my posing and I have
what they call a sleeper physique right
so you know I'm wearing a hoodie I'm not
trying to reveal the kind of shape I'm
in this stage in the offseason so so
we're just gonna say does David have the
ultimate sleeper physique maybe may you
know David I think not a lot enough
people are really talking about how
strong of a sleeper physique David
Thomas to has I mean he's really one of
the sleepers in the game the hoodie game
is strong and I think we're going to see
a big uh future for him in 2024 I you
know what I wouldn't bet against that
guy myself anyway moving on to a non-
aesthetic sport let's talk about high
rocks H rocks is one of the newer Sports
we cover is it a strength sport is it an
endurance sport it's it's hybrid there
certainly functional fitness right the
races are always the same it's a lot of
running some functional movements rowing
Etc sleds you name it wall balls who fun
fun fun let's talk about how High rocks
game is changing a little bit because
when High Rock first came on the scene
they recruited a lot of like obstacle
course racing veterans right Hunter
McIntyre comes to mind one of the best
OCR you know OCR athletes in history we
talked a few episodes ago about how some
CrossFit athletes are maybe making the
switch over or implying they're going to
and we saw that this past weekend
because Christy o Connell former
CrossFit Games athlete I believe she had
five top 10 games finishes by the way
Christy oconnell based out of Kentucky
my home state her mom was also a former
CrossFit Games athlete in the Masters
division fun fun Christy oconnell has
stepped back from competitive CrossFit
has stepped into competitive High rocks
and wins her debut
race and I think we were talking about
like what happens if a lot of these
crossfitters a lot of these CrossFit
athletes who maybe getting maybe getting
up there in like Master's age divisions
they're not competing in the open so
anymore you know maybe they want a
little bit less stress on the body some
of the less heavy weights and maybe
because like strength can Peak and
explosiveness Peaks earlier than
endurance does right so what happens
with these athletes who are super fit
super strong get a little bit older it's
easier for them to maintain and train
endurance than it is say you know
cleaning 300 pounds for reps what
happens when they try H rocks Christy
oconnell is giving us a taste of that
turns out they win by like three
minutes like freaking dominating it's
like coming out your and it's like when
one of those folks wins their first they
make their Marathon debut and they set a
world record not exactly what happened
here but also not far off from
it yeah not far off from it her she
scored a time of 10437 now there's only
been a few female athletes that have
ever broken the sub one hour mark and
those are pro hro athletes like that is
what they do now the difference for H
Rock versus CrossFit like you mentioned
where you don't have to worry as much
about strength there is no barbell in h
rocks at no point do you touch a barbell
so that's not part of the game and also
different from Crossfit where a lot of
the time if you compete at high level
CrossFit there's going to be events that
you don't know they won't tell you what
an event is until you actually compete
in it h rock you know exactly what the
race is going to be every single time
you run it and you're only trying to get
better at the exact same run in the same
order every time so it is a different
beast from Crossfit but like yeah as you
mentioned if any of the Masters athletes
from Crossfit or the people who are like
you know not as performing as well as
CrossFit like move over and compete in
high rocks like they could do well and
we've seen you know still topend uh
athletes in CrossFit compete at a hrock
event before like we've seen Chandler
Smith compete at a hro alongside Hunter
McIntyre who has the world record at
hrock and do really well I expect to see
more of that funneling from Crossfit to
H rocks as athletes move into the
Masters divisions I also want to point
out Christy oconnell is kind of like
built in a lab for high rocks right high
level CrossFit Games athlete five top 10
finishes clearly Has the strength but a
background in endurance sport she was a
Collegiate swimmer then she was a she
was also a competitive triathlete right
like she's one of those crossfitters who
was never the strongest on the field
with a barbell but was always going to
compete in the endurance events right so
like an endurance leaning CrossFit Games
athlete yeah that's pretty much the
archetype for high rocks right now I
think all right so David if you if
you're tier one first pick out of the
top CrossFit athletes right now to win
their debut H rocks if they were to
compete who would you pick Danielle
Brandon maybe that's a good pick that's
a
the thing is like I know Danielle
Brandon good great great endurance great
endurance I don't know I'm just going to
that's just like gut gut feeling I I say
Danielle Brandon although you know what
honestly Tia Clair Tumi like also up
there yeah yeah yeah I mean you just
reminded me like I my pack one pick one
would be Haley Adams now she might be
top of she might be top of mine for me
because you know she took a year off and
now she's gonna come back in 2024 and
I'm excited to see her compete but like
I've always been like you know if
there's ever an event where running is
involved it's always she's always going
to be my my first pick to take something
down but then you calling back you know
to some of the dominant athletes of
crossfit's past I would I think carry
Pierce would also be very good at
crushing a high Ro event because she is
also a very good I mean granted like
she's incredible with a barbell as well
but like I think she could crush an
endurance event I mean her her her
Atlanta performance is something that
sticks out in my mind forever when I
think of top CrossFit performances all
the love in the world to Carrie Pierce
Carrie Pierce is a personal friend love
Carrie Pierce amazing amazing athlete
right you look at the Atlanta event from
2020 where she really excelled and just
beat the field right like beat
everyone you're looking at higher skill
gymnastics there right you're looking at
her ability to just knock out pull-ups
unlike anybody else right you're looking
at her ability to do things like
handstand like Carri Pierce at one point
Carri Pierce could do 200 Kipping
handstand push-ups in a row without
coming off the wall like that's an
actual thing that she did so while she's
an accomplished Runner she's not for me
like that top tier like just in a pure
run I think she's not that tier of like
haly Adams you know was but H rock is so
heavily there like so heavily geared
toward running right there's other
stuff but like running can running will
win
you running wins High rocks all the
other events can lose you at can lose
you a high rocks race all right David if
running if running wins you H Rox then
get me Katherine Davis daughter on my
roster right now to just break every H
Rox record that's ever happened we got
to move on let's stop talking about
running I'm exhausted I'm out of breath
too much running let's talk about
lifting heavy barbells once Russell Orie
returning to the powerlifting platform
Phil give us a tail of tape what did he
do I'm so exhausted so or of course
competing in the 83 kilogram class at
the 2024 powerlifting America raw
Nationals who was returned to
powerlifting America he went 9 for9 a
perfect performance to get the gold
medal with an 860 kg raw total that by
the way an unofficial raw total world
record so it need it wasn't an ipf world
record because it wasn't done on an
international platform but unofficially
higher than the ipf world record uh he
also scored a 330 kilogram raw squat
which is n and a half kilograms more
than his current 320 a half kilogram ipf
world record so even though that's not
official he destroyed his current ipf
world record by 9 and a half kilograms
huge day and even though he won the
powerlifting raw Nationals for the sixth
time this was a sixth title even then he
still thinks that he didn't have his
best performance he actually said quote
about this performance this was probably
one of my worst
meets like okay this was probably one of
my worst meets I felt uncomfortable
Rusty my technique was all over the
place that's the quote so like okay two
unofficial World Records your sixth
national title and you're still
me me medium when this dude competes on
the international level again like which
is coming up soon this year good luck
everyone else good because like Russa
or's always been great but for some
reason or reasons he's got the biggest
chip on his shoulder right now and I
mean that in the in a such a
complimentary way Russa or he has proved
himself as one of the best living
powerlifters but there's something
Michael Jordan asked about him where
he's like Russell I love you to death
but you're like manufacturing reasons to
have a chip on your shoulder to motivate
yourself and I love it so much right
youever watch like the last dance when
they're talking about like Michael
Jordan having beef with someone and
they're like he might have made it up
like he might have taken it personally
and he might have made it I took that
personally yeah like Russell or he is
just he's like my technique wasn't bad
was bad I didn't feel good he's giving
himself reasons to go into his next
competition with like a chip on his
shoulder that he gave
himself that is an intense competitive
mindset and honestly I'm here for it I
am so here for it let's let's presume
that you know he continues to crush and
win everything and still be unhappy
about it I can't wait for him to just
dominate the world games in 2025 like
it'll be the first opportunity for
powerlifters at the world games and I
just like I'm all the chips all in on
orhe for sure because like okay you you
break multiple records it unofficially
whatever but you break these World
Records unbelievable performance if you
watch the videos it looks the it looks
clean like nothing looks off but he's
just like doesn't feel good like oh man
chip all in at the world games on Russ I
can't wait to like make an an AI
generated fake powerlifter just to
motivate Russ just to give him like
another rabbit to chase I love it I love
it well that brings us to the end of
this week's strength weekly for bar.com
I'm David Thomas toow joined by Phil
Blackman we'll bring you more coverage
next week uh and I'm going to keep
working on my sleeper physique
can keep working on
it